Guide to the Herbert Clarence Bradshaw Papers, 1922-1976 RL.00143
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Herbert Clarence Bradshaw papers
1922-1976
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Bradshaw, Herbert Clarence, 1908-1976
RL.00143
35 Linear Feet 70 boxes.
Herbert Clarence Bradshaw (1908-1976) was a white American author, historian, and journalist. This collection documents his personal and professional life through his subject files, which include a great deal of correspondence. A retired editor of the Durham Morning Herald, he was murdered in his home during a series of random shootings in Durham by a single individual in December 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
Access restricted. Addition 1987-0094 is unprocessed and requires additional arrangement, description, and/or screening. Contact Research Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Herbert Clarence Bradshaw papers were acquired by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library as gifts between 1977-1987.
Arrangement
The Herbert Clarence Bradshaw papers are arranged alphabetically.
Biographical / Historical
Herbert Clarence Bradshaw (1908-1976) was born on 7 November 1908 in Rice, Virginia. He graduated with a BA from Hampden-Sydney College in 1930, an MA in classical languages from the University of Virginia in 1933, and a LittD degree from Hampden-Sydney in 1967.
For twenty years, he taught and served as a principal in Virginia, and he later taught journalism at North Carolina State University. He became a full-time journalist circa 1949 as Sunday Feature Editor of the Durham Morning Herald and was Editorial Page Leader from 1964 until retiring in December 1973. After, he served as Contributing Editor of the Winston-Salem Journal and as a member of the Durham Redevelopment Commission. He was also a member of the Board of Directors of the Human Betterment League of NC, which promoted eugenics, and was President at the time of his death.
Bradshaw was killed on 22 December 1976 while helping his wife (Mildred Elizabeth Cunningham) wash dishes in their Durham home. James Willie Grace, a Durham native and convicted felon who was likely dealing with untreated schizophrenia, carried out a series of random shootings around Durham from December 10-22 (one other man was killed). He was arrested on 28 December and later convicted on three charges of felonious assault with intent to kill.
Bradshaw is the author of The History of Prince Edward County, Virginia (1955), History of Hampden-Sydney College, vol. I (1976), History of Farmville, VA (1948), Toward the Dawn: History of the First Quarter-Century of the NC State Association for the Blind, 1934-1960 (1961), and fifty articles from 1935-1976 on the histories of the Baptist Church, the Lions organization, and organizations for the blind in NC, and historical pieces on such topics as Patrick Henry, Thomas Jefferson, and historic houses.
Related Materials
Other parts of Bradshaw's papers are held by the Virginia Baptist Historical Society at the University of Richmond and the Library of Virginia.
Scope and Contents
Bradshaw's papers detail his involvement as a member of the NC Commission for the Blind for 18 years, a member of the Advisory Board for the Mary Duke Biddle Art Gallery for the Blind at the NC Museum of Art, President of the NC Society for the Prevention of Blindness, and member of the Board of Directors and President of the Human Betterment League of NC.
Many printed items--rosters, programs, clippings, and photographs--are scattered throughout the files, where they are integral parts of personal or organizational papers. Files on Durham (NC) include histories and correspondence on city and county government (1853-1973), the Chamber of Commerce, civitan and optimist clubs, Merchants Association, Public Library, and School Board; the latter includes a substantial series of folders on race relations and school desegregation. There are printed programs of cultural events held in Richmond, Durham, and Raleigh from 1929-1972, and programs, rosters, histories, minutes, and correspondence on Lions Club activities in Durham and throughout NC from 1922-1974.
Material prepared for the centennial edition of the Durham Morning Herald includes histories of local organizations (1805-1953). Bradshaw kept detailed diaries and correspondence on his Book Page and editorials from 1949-1973. Important among histories of the Civil War is his account of historic events in the Appomattox area, which he wrote for the centennial edition of the Farmville Herald (VA) in 1965; a longer local history account appears in that newspaper's sesquicentennial edition from 1948.
The Duke University files include professor Mason Crum's unpublished manuscript Washington Duke, along with Bradshaw's correspondence with faculty from 1949-1973. Correspondence with Dr. J. B. Rhine from 1963-1972 shows the development of his Foundation for Research on the Nature of Man.
This collection contains voluminous correspondence from 1922-1976, including signed letters from William O. Douglas; Dean Acheson; Dean Rusk; William P. Rogers; J. William Fulbright; NC Governors Luther Hodges, Terry Sanford, and Robert Scott; Senators Henry Jackson and B. Everett Jordan; Norman Mailer; and Douglas M. Knight. There is also correspondence with and the memoirs of Myrta Lockett Avary, author of A Virginia Girl in the Civil War. There is a morgue with hundreds of glossy photographs of contemporary writers.
There is correspondence on the 900-acre Virginia farm that he and his brother managed and his involvement with Hampden-Sydney College (both for 44 years). His writing of the history of the Baptist Church in NC (1805-1973) is included, along with correspondence on the Yates Baptist Association and the Watts Street Baptist Church from 1950-1971. His interest in genealogy led to lengthy correspondence on the genealogies of the Armistead, Bradshaw, Cunningham, Chambliss, Few, Fuqua, Lockett, McGehee, Marshall, Nash, Scarborough, Venable, and Walton families.
Addition 1987-0094 contains correspondence, notes, and printed material for the development of Durham and its commemoration of the US bicentennial in 1976. It also contains information concerning health care in NC and notes from various conferences held by the US State Department for news editors.
Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; Baptists -- North Carolina -- History; Blind -- Services for -- North Carolina; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Durham (N.C.) -- Race relations; Segregation in education -- Durham (N.C.); United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Bradshaw, Herbert Clarence, 1908-1976; Duke University; Durham Morning Herald; Hampden-Sydney College
- Biographical and Autobiographical Information
  Scope and Contents
  Vita, letters, articles, awards, clippings, a formal photograph, and other items. Also includes an inventory of the collection and the Library of Virginia inventory.
- Subject Files
  Bradshaw's subject files as an author, historian, and journalist. Organized into subseries based on his major subject areas, like the Baptist Church; blindness and public health; Durham, the Durham Morning Herald, race relations, and North Carolina; Duke University, Hampden-Sydney College, and the University of North Carolina; the Civil War; genealogies; the Lions Club; and press associations.
  - Association for the Preservation of Virginia Antiquities, 1927-1929, 1950-1955, 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Avary, Myrta Lockett, 1846, 1866, 1903, 1933, 1940-1946
    - Correspondence (Box 2)
    - Legal documents (Box 2)
    - Memoirs (Box 2)
    - Photos (Box 2)
    - Poetry (Box 2)
    - Writings (Box 2)
    - Sherwin article on Avary (Box 2)
  - Baptist Church (NC)
    - Baptist Church histories, 1930, 1935-1973 (Box 3)
    - Baptist State Convention of NC, 1960, 1971 (Box 3)
    - Churches of Durham, 1805-1951, 1952-1968, 1971-1972 (Box 3)
    - First Baptist Church of Durham, 1970-1973 (Box 3)
    - Greater Durham Evangelistic Crusade, 1965 (Box 3)
    - Religion, 1859, 1930, 1954-1973 (Box 3)
      Articles, news clippings, etc.
    - Watts Street Baptist Church, 1950-1970 (Box 4)
    - Yates Baptist Association, 1953-1971 (Box 5)
  - Blindness
    - Glaucoma clinics (Box 9)
    - National Society for the Prevention of Blindness, 1964-1973 (Box 6, Box 7)
    - National Society for the Prevention of Blindness (Box 52)
    - NC Association for the Blind, 1948-1974 (Box 8)
    - NC Association for the Blind, 1960-1967 (Box 9)
    - NC Association for the Blind: "The White Cane", 1947, 1956-1973 (Box 9)
    - NC Association for the Blind: Toward the Dawn: History of the NC State Association for the Blind, 1934-1960 (Box 11)
    - NC Commission for the Blind: Biennial Reports, 1950-1968 (Box 12-16)
    - NC Commission for the Blind: Manual (Box 12-16)
    - NC Commission for the Blind: Publications (Box 12-16)
    - NC Commission for the Blind: Vocational Rehabilitation Plan (Box 12-16)
    - NC Commission for the Blind and NC Bureau of Employment for the Blind: Quarterly Reports, 1964-1970 (Box 17, Box 18)
    - NC Eye and Human Tissue Bank, 1960-1971 (Box 9)
    - NC Society for the Prevention of Blindness, 1966-1974 (Box 10)
    - President Nixon's Proclamation: "Save your Vision Week, 1973" (Box 69)
    - The Seeing Eye, Inc., 1957-1958 (Box 18)
  - Bradshaw, Herbert Clarence
    - Book reviews scrapbook, 1931-1945 (Box 18)
    - Book reviews scrapbook, 1931-1945 (Box 69)
    - Personal and family clippings and memorabilia, 1952-1974 (Box 19)
    - Personal and family correspondence: Farm, 1929-1973 (Box 20, Box 21, Box 22)
    - Personal and family correspondence: General, 1922-1975 (Box 23, Box 24, Box 25, Box 26)
    - Speaking engagements, 1956-1973 (Box 27)
    - Writings, 1935-1976 (Box 28, Box 29)
  - Civil War
    - Bennitt Place, 1962-1964 (Box 30)
    - Civil War Centennial Commission, 1958-1965 (Box 30)
    - Confederate veterans reunions, 1929, 1932 (Box 30)
    - Farmville Herald centennial, 1965 (Box 30)
    - Farmville Herald sesquicentennial, 1948 (Box 30)
    - Fortifications at High Bridge, Appomattox River, 1865 (Box 30)
    - Johnston, Joseph E., 1959-1963 (Box 30)
    - NC Confederate Centennial Commission, 1958-1965 (Box 30)
    - Soldier's letter: "Tell Ma to send me some meat to boil with peas", 1864 April (Box 30)
  - Duke University
    - Correspondence with Duke faculty, 1949-1973 (Box 31)
    - General Telephone issue, 1972 (Box 31)
    - Foundation for Research on the Nature of Man (J. B. Rhine), 1963-1972 (Box 31)
    - Rule of Law Research Center (Arthur Larson), 1960, 1966 (Box 31)
    - Sanford, Terry, 1962, 1964, 1970-1972 (Box 31)
    - Washington Duke by Mason Crum, circa 1951 (Box 31)
  - Durham
    - Chamber of Commerce, 1961-1973 (Box 32)
    - City and County government, 1853-1953, 1957-1973 (Box 32)
    - Civitan and optimist clubs, 1952 (Box 32)
    - County Association for the Blind, 1949-1959 (Box 32)
    - Golden Age Society, 1956 (Box 32)
    - Merchants Association, 1956, 1969-1972 (Box 32)
    - NC College at Durham, 1950-1952, 1968 (Box 32)
    - All-America City Award, 1963 (Box 32)
    - Public Library, 1897-1936, 1953-1961 (Box 32)
    - Research Triangle, History of, 1953-1965 (Box 32)
    - Scarborough Nursery School, 1950 (Box 32)
    - School Board, 1951, 1965-1966 (Box 32)
    - School Study Committee, 1959-1960 (Box 32)
    - Social scene, 1960-1963, 1965 (Box 32)
    - United Fund campaign, 1962-1973 (Box 32)
  - Durham Morning Herald (NC)
    - Book Page, 1949, 1955-1973 (Box 33)
    - Book Page: Correspondence, 1950-1973 (Box 33)
    - Book reviews, 1931-1945 (Box 69)
    - Centennial Edition: Correspondence, 1953 (Box 34)
    - Centennial Edition: Histories of organizations, 1805-1953 (Box 34)
    - Diaries of book reviews and editorials, 1951-1972 (Box 35-36)
    - Editorial background material, 1929-1973 (Box 37-39)
    - Editorials, 1960-1967 (Box 39)
    - Editorials: Correspondence, 1949-1973 (Box 40)
    - Editorials, 1961-1963 (Box 39)
    - Features: Correspondence, 1953-1958, 1973 (Box 34)
    - Hickman, Frank S. "Just a Minute" column, 1952-1964 (Box 34)
    - Monthly Bulletins, 1950-1973 (Box 34)
    - Personnel directories, 1954-1973 (Box 34)
    - Style book, 1949 (Box 34)
  - Genealogies
    - Anderson (Box 41)
    - Armistead (Box 41)
    - Bradshaw (Box 41)
    - Carrington (Box 41)
    - Chambliss (Box 41)
    - Cunningham (Box 41)
    - Davis (Box 41)
    - Fain (Box 41)
    - Few (Box 41)
    - Flippen (Box 41)
    - Fuqua (Box 41)
    - Goodrich (Box 41)
    - Holcombe (Box 41)
    - Jenkins (Box 41)
    - Kennon (Box 41)
    - Kerr (Box 41)
    - Ligon (Box 41)
    - Lockett (Box 41)
    - Lockett genealogical chart (Box 69)
    - McGehee (Box 41)
    - Marshall (Box 41)
    - Nash (Box 41)
    - Osborne (Box 41)
    - Pallmore (Box 41)
    - Pankey (Box 41)
    - Scarborough (Box 41)
    - Thomson (Box 41)
    - Townes (Box 41)
    - Venable (Box 41)
    - Walker (Box 41)
    - Walthall (Box 41)
    - Walton (Box 41)
    - White (Box 41)
    - Wimbish (Box 41)
    - Woodson (Box 41)
  - Hampden-Sydney College, 1927-1973
    - Eggleston, Joseph DuPuy-McAllister, James Gray, 1929-1956 (Box 34)
    - Eggleston, Joseph DuPuy-McAllister, James Gray correspondence, 1929-1956 (Box 42)
    - Hampden-Sidney College, 1927-1973 (Box 42)
  - Lions
    - Apex to Zebulon, 1969-1972 (Box 43)
    - Conventions: National, 1960, 1970-1973 (Box 44)
    - Conventions: NC, 1961-1973 (Box 44)
    - District Governors, 1960-1972 (Box 45-46)
    - District 31G, 1960-1974 (Box 47)
    - Durham, 1950-1973 (Box 48-49)
    - History of Lionism, 1922-1960 (Box 50)
    - International, 1951-1952, 1966-1973 (Box 50)
    - International: Candidates for Director, 1970-1972 (Box 50)
    - International: Constitution and By-laws Committee, 1970-1972 (Box 50)
    - International: Politics, 1969-1970 (Box 50)
    - State Council, 1968-1973 (Box 51)
    - Zone Chairman, 1967-1970 (Box 51)
    - Zone club reports, 1967-1970 (Box 51)
  - North Carolina
    - Advisory Council to the Peace Corps, 1962-1964 (Box 53)
    - American Revolution Bicentennial Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 53)
    - Awards, 1966-1967, 1971 (Box 53)
    - Bowles for Governor, 1972 (Box 53)
    - Campbell College, 1962, 1967-1968, 1973 (Box 53)
    - Campbell College: Graham A. Barden Chair of Government (Box 28)
    - Campbell College: Graham A. Barden Chair of Government (Box 53)
    - Carolina Charter Tercentenary Commission (Box 28)
    - Carolina Charter Tercentenary Commission, 1961-1963 (Box 53)
    - Council on World Affairs, 1959-1963 (Box 53)
    - Democratic Party: Jefferson-Jackson Day Dinner, 1963 (Box 54)
    - Fund, 1966 (Box 54)
    - General Assembly: Interest Rate Study Commission, 1969-1973 (Box 54)
    - Governor's Conference on Planning for Higher Education, 1968 (Box 54)
    - Governor's Conference: Official Celebration of the 200th Anniversary of the Birth of George Washington, 1932 (Box 54)
    - Governor's Study Committee on Structure and Organization of Higher Education, 1971 (Box 54)
    - Historical Book Club of NC: Annual Town Meeting on Books (Box 42)
    - Historical Book Club of NC: Annual Town Meeting on Books, 1961-1971 (Box 54)
    - Huguenot Society, 1953-1972 (Box 55)
    - Human Betterment League of NC (Box 42)
    - Human Betterment League of NC, 1947-1976 (Box 56)
    - Literary and Historical Association, 1963-1972 (Box 56)
    - Mary Duke Biddle Gallery for the Blind, NC Museum of Art, 1966-1969, 1972 (Box 56)
    - Mary Duke Biddle Gallery for the Blind, NC Museum of Art (Box 69)
    - Political campaigns, 1972 (Box 56)
    - Political campaigns, 1972 (Box 59)
    - Rehabilitation Association, 1966-1967 (Box 56)
    - Salem Academy, 1969-1970 (Box 56)
    - Salem Academy (Box 66)
    - NC Society, Sons of the American Revolution, 1956-1971 (Box 56)
    - Study in vocational rehabilitation, 1965-1969 (Box 57)
    - Wake County courthouse speech: Professor Albert Coates, 1970 September 13 (Box 57)
  - Photographs
    - List of photographs (Box 58)
    - Buildings, places, scenes (Box 58)
    - Genre (Box 58)
    - People (Box 58-59)
    - Transportation (Box 59)
  - Press Associations
    - American Press Institute seminar, 1967 (Box 60)
    - National Foreign Policy Conference for Editors and Broadcasters, 1964, 1970, 1972 (Box 52)
    - Press associations, 1929-1963 (Box 60)
    - Southern Newspaper Publishers Association Foundation seminars for Southern journalists, 1967-1972 (Box 61)
    - Southern Newspaper Publishers Association Foundation seminars for Southern journalists (Box 67)
    - Southern Regional Education Board seminars for Southern journalists, 1966-1968 (Box 62)
    - Southern Regional Education Board seminars for Southern journalists (Box 67)
  - Public Health
    - Durham County TB and Health Association, 1952, 1954-1957 (Box 63)
    - Hospitals (NC) (Box 42)
    - Hospitals (NC), 1965-1972 (Box 63)
    - Medical education (NC), 1971 (Box 63)
    - National Health Council (Box 52)
    - National Health Council, 1967 (Box 63)
    - NC Comprehensive Health Planning Council, 1968-1971 (Box 63)
    - NC Comprehensive Health Planning Project, 1970 (Box 64)
    - NC Comprehensive Health Services, 1968-1969 (Box 65)
    - NC Comprehensive Health Services: Financing, 1969-1973 (Box 65)
    - Psychiatric hospitals (NC), 1957, 1966-1967 (Box 63)
    - Smoking and health, 1969 (Box 63)
  - Race Relations
    - Desegregation plan, Durham School Board, 1965 (Box 66)
    - Durham negro grievances on school integration, 1967-1969 (Box 66)
    - "Durham Plan", 1963 (Box 66)
    - National Commission on Civil Order riot report, 1968 (Box 66)
    - Segregation: Articles, 1954-1969 (Box 66)
    - Segregation: Richmond (VA) newspaper clippings, 1955 (Box 66)
  - Salvation Army cases from Social Services Department (Box 67)
  - State and local revenue potential: Southern Regional Education Board, 1969 (Box 67)
  - US Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, National Policy and Performance Council, 1968-1972 (Box 52)
  - US Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, National Policy and Performance Council, 1968-1972 (Box 68)
  - University of North Carolina
    - Black student movement, 1968 (Box 68)
    - Election of Trustees, 1966 (Box 68)
    - Installation of Chancellor Nelson E. Taylor, 1972 (Box 68)
    - Newsletter, 1970-1973 (Box 68)
  - Virginia Historical Society, 1967 (Box 68)
- Addition 1987-0094, 1976 (Box 70)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Access restricted. Materials require additional arrangement, description, and/or screening because they are unprocessed. Contact Research Services for more information.
  Correspondence, notes, and printed material for the development of Durham and its commemoration of the US bicentennial in 1976. Also includes information concerning health care in NC and notes from various conferences held by the US State Department for news editors.